Finding aid to New York City Women Community Activists Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00524
Sophia Smith Collection
New York City Women Community Activists Oral History Project oral histories
1970-2010
Sophia Smith Collection
Carroll, Tamar Wilder
SSC.MS.00524
0.438 linear feet (1 container)
This collection consists of interviews conducted by Tamar Carroll for her dissertation on women's community activism in New York City, circa 1955-1995, including activists involved in Mobilization For Youth on New York City's Lower East Side and members of the National Congress of Neighborhood Women.
Scope and Contents
This oral history collection consists of fourteen interviews conducted by Tamar Carroll for her dissertation on women's community activism in New York City, circa 1955-1995 for the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Included are interviews with activists involved in Mobilization For Youth, one of the country's first anti-poverty agencies founded in 1957 on New York City's Lower East Side to combat juvenile delinquency. Activists include Frances Fox Piven, Rosalyn Baxandall, attorneys Faith Colangelo and Nancy LeBlanc, and other MFY staff members. Also interviewed are members of the National Congress of Neighborhood Women of Brooklyn, N.Y., Sally Martinez Fisher and Ethel Velez. Materials include audio CDs and transcripts.
Additional Formats
Original audio recordings have been transferred to CD-ROM for research use; some content has been digitized.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The New York City Women Community Activists Oral Histories were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Tamar Wilder Carroll between 2005 and 2012.
Related Materials
Additional Mobilization for Youth interviews at Columbia University Oral History Archives (War on Poverty Project), New York, NY
Associated material is in the National Congress of Neighborhood Women Records and the Frances Piven Papers in the Sophia Smith Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
New York (N.Y.)--Social conditions--20th century; Poor--United States--Political activity--History--Sources; Public welfare--United States--History--Sources; Community development--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources; Urban renewal--United States--History--Sources; Oral history--Archival resources; CD-Roms; Oral histories; Electronic records; Computer media; Feminists--United States---History--20th century--Sources; Transcripts; articles; Juvenile delinquency -- United States -- History -- Sources; AbuBakr, Rashida Ismaili; Baxandall, Rosalyn Fraad, 1939; Birnbaum, Ezra; Colangelo, Faith; Dowery, Mary Anne; Fisher, Sally Martinez; Gore, Marilyn; Josephs, Barbara; LeBlanc, Nancy; Mizrahi, Terry; Piven, Frances Fox; Velez, Ethel; Mobilization for Youth--History--Sources; National Congress of Neighborhood Women--History--Sources; Sanchez, Digna; Wizner, Stephen
- Mobilization For Youth interviews, 2004-2010
  - Transcripts
    - Rashida Ismaili AbuBakr (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rosalyn Baxandall (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ezra Birnbaum (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mary Anne Dowery (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Marilyn Gore (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Barbara Josephs (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Terry Mizrahi (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Frances Fox Piven (2 parts) (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Interviews
    - MFY attorneys Faith Colangelo, Nancy LeBlanc interview notes, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Digna Sanchez interview, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Stephen Wizner interview, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Audio recordings on CDs of interviews with Josephs, Piven, Gore, Dowery, AbuBakr, Baxandall, Mizrahi, and Sanchez (Box 1, Folder 13)
- National Congress of Neighborhood Women interviews, 2004-2007
  - Transcripts of interview with Sally Martinez Fisher, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Transcript of interview with Ethel Velez, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Audio recordings on CDs of interviews with Fisher and Velez (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Article, "Unlikely Allies: Forging a Multiracial, Class-based Women's Movement in 1970s Brooklyn" by Tamar Carroll (chapter published in Feminist Coalitions, ed. Stephanie Gilmore), 2007 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Women and Social Movements web project materials including emails, article, and excerpts of interviews with Fisher, Velez and Rosemary Jackson, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Copies of audio files and electronic transcripts on CDs (Box 1, Folder 20)